Stephen Larroque: So, something I say sometimes is that I'm living outside of time.
Stephen Larroque: So, something I say sometimes is that I'm living outside of time.
Hella Kemper: This is Stephen Larroque.
Hella Kemper: Das ist Stephen Larroque.
HK: He says of himself that he lives outside of time, which sounds kind of mysterious, Nina.
HK: Er sagt von sich selbst, dass er außerhalb der Zeit lebt, hört sich irgendwie geheimnisvoll an, Nina.
Nina Lennartz: Yes, mysterious, but also complicated and painful.
Nina Lennartz: Ja, geheimnisvoll, aber auch kompliziert und schmerzhaft.
SL: Outside of school I had no activities, because it was very stressful to go to school all the time at a fixed time.
SL: Outside of school I had no activities, because it was very straining to go to school all the time at a fixed time.
NL: Larroque is telling us here how exhausting it was for him to go to school at the same time every day.
NL: Larroque erzählt hier, wie anstrengend es für ihn war, jeden Tag um dieselbe Uhrzeit zur Schule zu gehen.
NL: It took all his strength.
NL: Es raubte ihm all seine Kraft.
SL: Because of that, I used all my energy and health to just go to school.
SL: Because of that I used all my energy and health to just attend school.
SL: And outside of school there's nothing.
SL: And outside of school there's nothing.
SL: I had no life beyond.
SL: I had no life beyond.
NL: That was because his circadian rhythm, his inner sleep-wake rhythm, was not in sync with the rest of the world.
NL: Das lag daran, dass sein circadianer Rhythmus, also sein innerer Schlaf-Wach-Rhythmus, nicht mit dem der restlichen Welt synchron ist.
NL: As a kid, he was so tired after school, he would fall asleep right at home, no matter where.
NL: Als Kind war er nach der Schule deswegen oft hundemüde, ist zu Hause direkt eingeschlafen, egal wo.
NL: And he says he practically didn't have a life outside of school.
NL: Und er sagt, dass er praktisch kein Leben außerhalb der Schule hatte.
HK: What does that mean that his inner rhythm is not synchronous with the rest of the world?
HK: Was heißt das, dass sein innerer Rhythmus nicht synchron verläuft zu dem der restlichen Welt?
NL: Our sleep-wake behaviors are driven by this circadian rhythm within us.
NL: Unser Schlaf-Wach-Verhalten wird eben von diesem circadianer Rhythmus in uns gesteuert.
NL: Circadian, because the rhythm takes about 24 hours, sometimes a little longer, sometimes a little shorter.
NL: Circadianer, weil der Rhythmus circa 24 Stunden dauert, mal ein bisschen länger, mal ein bisschen kürzer.
NL: The average is about 24.2.
NL: Durchschnittlich liegt er ungefähr bei 24,2.
HK: But our world is being timed to an exact 24-hour rhythm, not a rough one.
HK: Aber unsere Welt ist nach einem exakten 24-Stunden-Rhythmus getaktet, nicht einem ungefähren.
NL: That's right.
NL: Genau.
NL: And this is possible because external factors like daylight, but also diet and exercise, are adjusting our internal clocks to 24 hours, so to speak.
NL: Und das ist möglich, weil äußere Faktoren wie das Tageslicht, aber auch Ernährung und Bewegung unsere inneren Uhren auf 24 Stunden nachjustieren sozusagen.
NL: Light is the decisive factor in this, because it affects our most important internal clock, the subrachiasmatic core in the hypothalamus.
NL: Licht ist dabei der entscheidende Faktor, weil er auf unsere wichtigste innere Uhr einwirkt, den subrachiasmatischen Kern im Hypothalamus.
NL: When light hits our retina, signals from there also reach this very core.
NL: Wenn Licht auf unsere Netzhaut fällt, gelangen von dort auch Signale zu genau diesem Kern.
NL: And that then leads to the production of the sleep hormone melatonin being stopped.
NL: Und das führt dann dazu, dass die Produktion des Schlafhormons Melatonin gestoppt wird.
NL: So we're going to wake up.
NL: Wir werden dann also wach.
NL: But there's a problem now.
NL: Jetzt gibt es allerdings ein Problem.
NL: This synchronization doesn't work for all people.
NL: Diese Synchronisation funktioniert nicht bei allen Menschen.
NL: They live in their own time.
NL: Sie leben in ihrer eigenen Zeit.
HK: Good morning or good evening, depending on where your internal clock is or where you are in the world.
HK: Guten Morgen oder guten Abend, je nachdem, wo der Zeiger ihrer inneren Uhr gerade steht oder wo auf der Welt sie sich gerade befinden.
HK: My name is Hella Kemper and I'm going to walk you through today's episode of the Know-it-Time podcast.
HK: Mein Name ist Hella Kemper und ich begleite Sie durch die heutige Folge des Zeitwissen-Podcasts.
HK: We want to try to understand sleep better.
HK: Wir wollen versuchen, den Schlaf besser zu verstehen.
HK: We meet people whose inner clock ticks differently.
HK: Wir treffen Menschen, deren innere Uhr anders tickt.
HK: Our author Nina Lennertz spoke to a sleep specialist.
HK: Unsere Autorin Nina Lennertz hat mit einem Schlafmediziner gesprochen.
HK: She wanted to know when you stop talking about sleep deprivation, when it's a real sleep disorder, and what you can do about it.
HK: Sie wollte wissen, wann man nicht mehr von schlechten Einschlafen spricht, sondern es sich um eine richtige Schlafstörung handelt und was man dagegen tun kann.
HK: And because many of us are up at night, you get the best sleeping tips from our author Tobias Hürther.
HK: Und weil viele von uns hin und wieder nachts wach liegen, bekommen Sie die besten Schlaftipps von unserem Autor Tobias Hürther.
HK: He's a philosopher, and watched nights are not entirely foreign to him, I think.
HK: Er ist Philosoph und durchwachte Nächte sind ihm da, glaube ich, nicht ganz fremd.
HK: And Christoph Drösser asks in his Impossible column why some of us turn to sleep.
HK: Und Christoph Drösser fragt in seiner Unmöglichen Kolumne, warum manche von uns Schlaf wandeln.
HK: So Nina, the French neuroscientist Stéphane Larroque, is having trouble adapting his individual day-night rhythm to our 24-hour day.
HK: Nina, der französische Neurowissenschaftler Stéphane Larroque hat also Probleme, seinen individuellen Tag-Nacht-Rhythmus an unseren 24-Stunden-Tag anzupassen.
HK: Sounds like a very busy life.
HK: Klingt nach einem anstrengenden Leben.
NL: Yeah, he's 24 now.
NL: Ja, er hat nun 24.
NL: Non-24 is a disorder, this circadian rhythm that's very common in blind people.
NL: Non-24, das ist eine Störung, dieses zirkadianen Rhythmus, die sehr häufig bei blinden Menschen auftritt.
NL: But Larroque is not blind.
NL: Aber Larroque ist nicht blind.
NL: No, no, he can see without restrictions.
NL: Nein, nein, er kann ohne Einschränkungen sehen.
NL: But that's one of the rare cases.
NL: Damit gehört er aber zu einem der seltenen Fälle.
NL: Non-24 is much more common in blind people.
NL: Bei blinden Menschen kommt Non-24 viel öfter vor.
NL: According to a 2016 article, up to 70 percent of blind people who can't see light at all suffer from it.
NL: Laut einem Fachartikel von 2016 leiden bis zu 70 Prozent der Blinden, die überhaupt kein Licht mehr wahrnehmen können darunter.
NL: The adjustment of their internal clocks by the light falls off, meaning their internal rhythm runs independently.
NL: Die Anpassung ihrer inneren Uhren durch das Licht fällt aus, heißt, ihr innerer Rhythmus läuft dann unabhängig davon.
NL: If someone has a circadian rhythm of 24.5 hours, for example, their sleep and wake times shift by 30 minutes every day.
NL: Hat jemand einen zirkadianen Rhythmus von 24,5 Stunden, verschieben sich seine Schlaf- und Aufwachzeiten beispielsweise jeden Tag um 30 Minuten.
HK: So, in summary, the sleep-wake rhythm of these people is independent of the outer day-night rhythm.
HK: Also nochmal zusammengefasst, der Schlaf-Wachrhythmus dieser Menschen läuft unabhängig vom äußeren Tag-Nacht-Rhythmus ab.
HK: Sometimes it's okay, but most of the time it's not.
HK: Mal passt es, meistens aber nicht.
NL: Exactly, so in the example of a 24.5-hour rhythm, it takes 48 days for the inner rhythm, practically the inner night and the inner day to match the outer.
NL: Genau, also bei dem Beispiel einer Rhythmus-Dauer von 24,5 Stunden dauert es 48 Tage, bis der innere Rhythmus, praktisch die innere Nacht und der innere Tag mit dem äußeren wieder übereinstimmt.
NL: And then it starts all over again and moves on.
NL: Und dann geht das Ganze wieder von vorne los und verschiebt sich weiter.
HK: Sounds exhausting to the organism, but let's get back to the cause of this rhythm disorder.
HK: Klingt anstrengend für den Organismus, aber lass uns doch noch einmal auf die Ursache dieser Rhythmusstörung zurückkommen.
HK: Non24 is common in blind people, but Stephen Larroque, as we just said, can see.
HK: NON24 kommt häufig bei blinden Menschen vor, aber Stephen Larroque, das haben wir ja gerade schon gesagt, kann sehen.
NL: Yeah, and for a long time, he didn't know what was going on with him.
NL: Ja, und lange Zeit wusste er auch überhaupt nicht, was mit ihm los ist.
NL: Non24 is sometimes not even diagnosed in blind people, or at least not for a long time.
NL: NON24 wird auch bei blinden Menschen manchmal gar nicht oder zumindest lange Zeit nicht diagnostiziert.
NL: Stephen Larroque was diagnosed in his mid-20s.
NL: Stephen Larroque hat seine Diagnose dann mit Mitte 20 bekommen.
NL: Why exactly NON24 is now also present in people who see is still unclear.
NL: Warum genau NON24 jetzt auch bei sehenden Menschen vorkommt, das ist immer noch nicht klar.
NL: Larroque himself thinks it's genetic.
NL: Larroque selbst geht davon aus, dass es bei ihm genetisch bedingt ist.
NL: His father and grandmother were said to have had a very similar sleep-walking behavior to him.
NL: Sein Vater und seine Großmutter sollen nämlich ein ganz ähnliches Schlafwachverhalten gehabt haben wie er.
SL: His friends even joked about his father being a vampire because he slept behind closed curtains so often during the day.
SL: Seine Freunde haben sogar Witze darüber gemacht, dass sein Vater ein Vampir sei, weil er so oft tagsüber hinter zugezogenen Jalousien schlief.
NL: For a long time, Larroque's father was unemployed.
NL: Lange Zeit war Larroques Vater arbeitslos.
NL: That's what happens to a lot of people in the NON24 community, he says.
NL: So ergeht es vielen Menschen in der NON24-Community, sagt er.
NL: After all, it's not easy right now to find a job that fits a shifted sleep pattern or to keep a job that forces you to live permanently against your own internal clock.
NL: Schließlich ist es jetzt auch nicht gerade leicht, einen Job zu finden, der zu einem verschobenen Schlafrhythmus passt oder eine Arbeit zu halten, die einen zwingt, dauerhaft gegen die eigene innere Uhr zu leben.
HK: And how is that going with Stephen Larroque himself?
HK: Und wie läuft das bei Stephen Larroque selbst?
HK: Did his life get easier after the diagnosis?
HK: Wurde sein Leben nach der Diagnose einfacher?
NL: So for the first time, he actually went on in the big picture as before, just trying to adjust to the rhythm of his environment, against his inner clock.
NL: Also erstmal hat er tatsächlich im Großen und Ganzen weitergemacht wie bisher und einfach versucht, sich dem Rhythmus seiner Umgebung anzupassen, gegen seine innere Uhr.
NL: That meant for him that he couldn't make reliable plans because he never knew if he might be asleep or tired.
NL: Das hieß für ihn, dass er keine zuverlässigen Pläne machen konnte, weil er nie wusste, ob er vielleicht einschläft oder müde ist.
NL: That was very chaotic.
NL: Das war sehr chaotisch.
SL: There were a lot of problems, both with my girlfriend and with the university.
SL: Es gab viele Probleme, sowohl mit meiner Freundin als auch mit der Universität.
SL: When I came to the reading room, I didn't have to sleep very often.
SL: Wenn ich zu den Lektüren kam, musste ich sehr oft nicht schlafen.
SL: I didn't have to sleep.
SL: Ich musste nicht schlafen.
SL: I was not sleeping.
SL: Ich schlief nicht.
SL: Sometimes I would sleep when I was reading.
SL: Manchmal schlief ich, wenn ich in der Lektüre gewesen wäre.
NL: It was hard for his relationship with his then girlfriend, who he's married to now.
NL: Es war schwer für die Beziehung mit seiner damaligen Freundin, mit der er heute verheiratet ist.
NL: But there were problems with sleep disturbances in his studies, too.
NL: Aber auch in seinem Studium gab es Probleme durch die Schlafstörungen.
NL: Sometimes he went to class without sleeping at all.
NL: Manchmal ist er zu Vorlesungen gegangen, ohne überhaupt geschlafen zu haben.
NL: Or sometimes he slept while he was supposed to be in college.
NL: Oder manchmal hat er geschlafen, während er eigentlich auch in der Uni sein sollte.
SL: I had a network of friends who sent me notes.
SL: Ich hatte ein Netzwerk von Freunden, die mir Noten geschickt haben.
SL: I had to find strategies to overcome these problems.
SL: Ich musste Strategien finden, um diese Probleme zu überwinden.
NL: So Larroque had to think of strategies to live with his shifting pace.
NL: Larroque musste sich also Strategien überlegen, um mit seinem verschobenen Rhythmus leben zu können.
NL: He had, for example,
NL: Er hatte z.B.
NL: a network of friends who wrote for him in college.
NL: ein Netzwerk von Freunden, die für ihn in der Uni mitgeschrieben haben.
NL: Very difficult.
NL: Sehr aufwendig.
NL: Yeah, that was it.
NL: Ja, das war es.
NL: And it was also very exhausting, so Larroque had heart problems.
NL: Und es war auch sehr anstrengend, sodass Larroque Probleme mit seinem Herzen bekommen hat.
NL: He says his heart problems only got better when he had nights where he could sleep well and for a long time.
NL: Die Herzprobleme wurden nur besser, wenn er Nächte hatte, in denen er gut und lange schlafen konnte, sagt er.
NL: So his rhythm was quite in line with the day-night rhythm of all of us.
NL: Sein Rhythmus also gerade relativ im Einklang war mit dem Tag-Nacht-Rhythmus von uns allen.
NL: So Larroque started trying to better control his sleeping and waking hours and adjust to our normal 24-hour rhythm in quotes.
NL: Da hat Larroque dann angefangen zu versuchen, seine Einschlaf- und Aufwachzeiten besser zu kontrollieren und eben unserem in Anführungsstrichen normalen 24-Stunden-Rhythmus anzupassen.
HK: But how can you do that, adjust your biological rhythm?
HK: Aber wie kann man das schaffen, seinen biologischen Rhythmus anzupassen?
NL: So for completely blind people who are now 24, there's a sleep remedy that's effective against the disorder.
NL: Also für völlig erblindete Menschen, die nun 24 haben, gibt es ein Schlafmittel, das wirksam gegen die Störung ist.
NL: It's called Tazimelton, but it's not approved for people who can still perceive light.
NL: Es heißt Tazimelton und ist aber nicht für Menschen zugelassen, die Licht noch wahrnehmen können.
NL: So that's not even true of Steffen Larroque.
NL: Kommt also auch für Steffen Larroque nicht in Frage.
NL: He helps himself primarily with light therapy.
NL: Er behilft sich vor allem mit Lichttherapie.
NL: When he wakes up, he puts on a device, which is a type of glasses, that radiates light to his eyes almost all day.
NL: Nach dem Aufwachen zieht er ein Gerät an, das ist so eine Art Brille, die seine Augen dann fast den ganzen Tag mit Licht bestrahlt.
NL: He wore it during our interview, for example.
NL: Die hatte er zum Beispiel auch während unseres Interviews an.
NL: At night, he makes sure to get as much germ light as possible.
NL: Abends wiederum achtet er darauf, sich möglichst Keimlicht auszuliefern.
NL: He wears them when he has to be out at night, like a special sunglasses with red glasses.
NL: Dafür trägt er, wenn er abends draußen sein muss, zum Beispiel eine spezielle Sonnenbrille mit roten Gläsern.
NL: So everyday things like going to the movies at night are out of his mind.
NL: So alltägliche Sachen wie abends ins Kino zu gehen, fallen für ihn aus.
HK: So he can't lead a completely normal life?
HK: Also ein komplett normales Leben kann er gar nicht führen?
NL: No, not quite.
NL: Nein, nicht ganz.
NL: But it helps him a lot today to know that it's not about his personality that he wasn't lazy when he wanted to sleep during the day or had to.
NL: Aber es hilft ihm heute sehr zu wissen, dass es nicht an seiner Persönlichkeit liegt, dass er als Kind nicht faul war, als er tagsüber schlafen wollte oder musste.
NL: The rhythm disorder is part of him, but not part of his personality.
NL: Die Rhythmusstörung ist zwar ein Teil von ihm, aber nicht ein Teil seiner Persönlichkeit.
NL: He's also been on the internet, sharing with people who are also now 24.
NL: Außerdem ist er in Online-Communities unterwegs und tauscht sich mit Menschen aus, die ebenfalls nun 24 haben.
HK: You're normal in your abnormality.
HK: Man ist normal in seiner Abnormalität.
HK: So a sentence that we could all remember, with or without sleep disorder.
HK: Also ein Satz, den wir uns alle merken könnten, mit oder ohne Schlafstörung.
NL: Yeah, that's right, I think that's very nice to say.
NL: Ja, genau, das finde ich auch sehr schön gesagt.
NL: And I took something else from the conversation with Steffen Larroque that I might be able to translate into my own life.
NL: Und ich habe noch etwas anderes aus dem Gespräch mit Steffen Larroque mitgenommen, das ich vielleicht mal auf mein eigenes Leben übertragen werde.
NL: He and his wife have a rule that I find very charming.
NL: Seine Frau und er haben eine Regel, die ich sehr charmant finde.
NL: Because you never fight at night.
NL: Sie streiten nämlich nie am Abend.
NL: When a conflict somehow collapses, they always postpone it to the next day.
NL: Wenn sich ein Konflikt irgendwie zusammenbraut, verschieben sie ihn immer auf den nächsten Tag.
NL: Because in the morning, you can better resolve conflicts, Larroque says, also because of our circadian rhythm.
NL: Am Morgen könne man Konflikte nämlich besser lösen, meint Larroque, auch aufgrund unseres zirkadianen Rhythmus.
HK: Yeah, I think it's a good idea too.
HK: Ja, finde ich auch eine gute Idee.
HK: And we all have a circadian rhythm after all.
HK: Und einen zirkadianen Rhythmus haben wir schließlich alle.
HK: And he also determines, for example, whether we're owls or lizards, so we go to bed early or late.
HK: Und er bestimmt zum Beispiel auch darüber, ob wir Eulen oder Lerchen sind, also früh oder spät ins Bett gehen.
NL: That's right, the rhythm is determined by our genetics.
NL: Genau, der Rhythmus ist durch unsere Genetik bestimmt.
NL: So science can even determine if someone is an owl or a lizard by using a hair sample.
NL: Die Wissenschaft kann also mittels einer Haarprobe sogar feststellen, ob jemand Eule oder Lerche ist.
NL: We all have different preferred bedtime.
NL: Wir haben alle unterschiedliche bevorzugte Einschlafzeiten.
NL: And everything in a time window from 9 p.m. to 1 a.m. at most is also quite normal at first, says Ingo Fieze.
NL: Und alles in einem Zeitfenster von 21 bis höchstens 1 Uhr ist auch erst mal ganz normal, sagt Ingo Fieze.
NL: He runs the sleep medicine center at Berlin Charité.
NL: Er leitet das Schlafmedizinische Zentrum an der Berliner Charité.
Ingo Fietze: It's in our genes, it's fixed, it's not changing much.
Ingo Fietze: Das ist in unseren Genen, das ist festgelegt, das ändert sich auch nicht wesentlich.
IF: There are only two shifts in life.
IF: Es gibt nur zwei Verschiebungen im Lebensalter.
IF: One is when I was a teenager, say between 13.
IF: Das eine ist als Jugendlicher, sagen wir zwischen 13.
IF: and 19.
IF: und 19.
IF: Age, I'm going to be an owl automatically, I prefer to go to bed between 10:00 and 24:00.
IF: Lebensjahr, werde ich automatisch eine Eule, gehe am liebsten zwischen 22 und 24 Uhr ins Bett.
IF: And as I get older, I say 55 years, this rhythm moves back a little bit forward.
IF: Und als Älterer, sage ich Ü55, verschiebt sich dieser Rhythmus wieder etwas nach vorn.
HK: Yeah, and what if I like to go to bed much later, so not between 9:00 and 1:00?
HK: Ja, und was ist dann, wenn ich gern viel später ins Bett gehe, also nicht zwischen 21 und 1 Uhr?
NL: Then there could be a shift forward or backward of your circadian rhythm.
NL: Dann könnte es sein, dass eine Verschiebung nach vorne oder nach hinten von deinem zirkadianen Rhythmus vorliegt.
NL: And then you talk about a circadian sleep rhythm disorder, like 24 is now a one.
NL: Und dann spricht man von einer zirkadianen Schlafwachrhythmusstörung, wie auch nun 24 eine ist.
IF: When young people say I can only go to bed at two or three, I can't go to bed before, I can't sleep at all, so we're starting from a shifted sleep rhythm, not a owl.
IF: Wenn junge Leute sagen, ich kann nur um zwei oder drei ins Bett, vorher geht das nicht, da kann ich gar nicht einschlafen, da gehen wir nicht mehr von einer Eule aus, sondern von einem verschobenen Schlafwachrhythmus.
NL: It can happen that the internal rhythm of sleep is genetically engineered to the point that their biological night always doesn't start until 3:00.
NL: Es kann vorkommen, dass der innere Schlafwachrhythmus genetisch so beschaffen ist, dass ihre biologische Nacht immer erst um drei Uhr beginnt.
NL: However, according to Vize, young people who often have the problem of going to bed very late are much more likely to postpone their period by sitting at their computer or cell phone until four o'clock at night.
NL: Bei Jugendlichen, die oft das Problem haben, dass sie erst sehr spät ins Bett gehen, kommt es laut Vize allerdings viel häufiger vor, dass sie ihre Phase sozusagen selber weiter nach hinten verschieben, indem sie immer bis vier Uhr nachts vom Computer oder am Handy sitzen.
NL: Delayed sleep rhythm is also often the problem of shiftworkers or night workers whose biological sleep rhythm is constantly disturbed by their working hours.
NL: Von einem verschobenen Schlafwachrhythmus sind auch oft Schicht- oder NachtarbeiterInnen betroffen, deren biologischer Schlafwachrhythmus ja aufgrund ihrer Arbeitszeiten ständig gestört wird.
NL: So night becomes day and day becomes night for them?
NL: Für die wird dann die Nacht zum Tag und der Tag zur Nacht?
NL: That's right, you can compare it a little bit to having a jet lag all the time, and then it's not, or at least it's very difficult to reconcile with being active during the day.
NL: Genau, man kann es vielleicht ein bisschen damit vergleichen, als hätte man ständig ein Jetlag und das ist dann gar nicht oder zumindest nur sehr schwer damit zu vereinbaren, tagsüber aktiv zu sein.
NL: Ingo Vietze gave an example from his own experience of treatment.
NL: Ingo Vietze hat ein Beispiel aus seiner eigenen Behandlungserfahrung genannt.
IF: Fördner worked the night shift for 30 years, lost his job, retired to Germany and they said, "You're looking for a new job".
IF: Fördner hat 30 Jahre Nachtschicht gemacht, hat seinen Job verloren, ist zur deutschen Rente gegangen und die haben gesagt, suchen Sie einen neuen Job.
If he didn't find one and the pension recommended, you'll have to take a day's nap.
IF: Er hat keinen gefunden und die Rente hat empfohlen, müssen Sie halt einen Tagesschop nehmen.
IF: Did he try it, did he not tolerate it, and then he came to us and said, "Doctor, what do we do now?"
IF: Hat er auch probiert, hat er nicht toleriert und kam dann zu uns und hat gesagt, Doktor, was machen wir jetzt?
IF: And then I actually wrote him a test that he obviously would not be a day person from being a night person anymore, because he's been doing that for 30 years and if the German pension is there or the employment agency can't find him a job,
IF: Und dann habe ich ihm tatsächlich einen Test geschrieben, dass er offensichtlich aus diesem Nachtmenschen wird kein Tagmensch mehr, weil das hat er einfach 30 Jahre gemacht und wenn die deutsche Rente da oder die Arbeitsvermittlung keinen Job für ihn findet,
If he wants to be charged.
IF: dann möchte er berentet werden.
NL: If your body tells you to go to sleep at four o'clock, but you're forced to show up at work at eight o'clock, you're logically getting too little sleep and then you're also sleeping.
NL: Wenn der eigene Körper einem anzeigt, um vier Uhr schlafen zu gehen, man aber gezwungen ist, um acht Uhr bei der Arbeit zu erscheinen, bekommt man logischerweise zu wenig Schlaf ab und dann auch eine Schlafstörung.
IF: The problem today is that we still have too little flexibility in working hours, that young people who are more likely to go to bed later still have to go to school early at seven or eight.
IF: Das Problem in der heutigen Zeit ist ja, dass wir immer noch zu wenig flexible Arbeitszeiten haben, dass Jugendliche, die eher eine spätere Bettzeit haben, immer noch früh um sieben oder acht in die Schule müssen.
NL: But not every sleep disorder is a disturbance of circadian rhythm.
NL: Aber nicht jede Schlafstörung ist dann gleich eine Störung des zirkadianen Rhythmus.
NL: According to Ingo Vieze, these disorders occur, and then you talk about insomnia, even more often.
NL: Laut Ingo Vieze kommen solche Störungen, dann spricht man von einer Insomnie, sogar häufiger vor.
NL: People with this condition may not sleep well or wake up often at night.
NL: Betroffene können schlecht einschlafen oder wachen häufig in der Nacht auf.
NL: The reasons can be, for example, mental illness or a stroke or simply poor sleep hygiene.
NL: Gründe können dann zum Beispiel auch seelische Krankheiten oder Schicksalsschläge oder auch einfach eine schlechte Schlafhygiene sein.
HK: Sleep hygiene, so what would be a good sleep hygiene?
HK: Schlafhygiene, also was wäre eine gute Schlafhygiene?
NL: For example, it would be good to pay attention to rest during sleep and to have regular bedtimes.
NL: Gut wäre zum Beispiel auf Ruhe zu achten während des Schlafs und auch regelmäßige Einschlafzeiten zu haben.
HK: And when do you know you have a sleep disorder?
HK: Und ab wann merkt man denn, dass man eine Schlafstörung hat?
HK: I mean, I can get a bad night's sleep sometimes, and I know that.
HK: Ich meine hin und wieder schlecht einschlafen können, das kenne ich auch.
NL: Ingo Vieze has a relatively simple rule for this.
NL: Dafür hat Ingo Vieze eine relativ einfache Regel.
NL: If you have trouble falling asleep or falling asleep at least three times a week and you don't change it within four to 12 months, even though you're taking care of your sleep hygiene, you should seek help.
NL: Wer nämlich mindestens dreimal die Woche Probleme beim Durchschlafen oder Einschlafen hat und bei dem sich das innerhalb von vier bis zwölf Monaten nicht ändert, obwohl man eben auf seine Schlafhygiene achtet, der sollte sich Hilfe suchen.
NL: After such a long period of sleep problems, you're talking about chronic sleep disorder.
NL: Ab so einem langen Zeitraum mit Schlafproblemen spricht man nämlich dann schon von einer chronischen Schlafstörung.
HK: So to prevent this from happening, I'm going to talk to Tobias Hürther, who's a time science author and has written the book You Are What You Sleep.
HK: Damit das nicht passiert, spreche ich jetzt mit Tobias Hürther, er ist Zeitwissenautor und hat das Buch geschrieben Du bist, was du schläfst.
HK: He knows some scientifically sound sleep tips for anyone without adult sleep disorders.
HK: Er kennt einige wissenschaftlich fundierte Schlaftipps für alle ohne ausgewachsene Schlafstörung.
HK: Hi, Tobias. What is it?
HK: Hallo Tobias.
I'm going to tell you something.
Tobias Hürther: Hallo Hella.
HK: Tobias, how did you sleep last night?
HK: Tobias, wie hast du die letzte Nacht geschlafen?
TH: In some ways good, so I've slept enough, eight hours.
TH: In mancher Hinsicht gut, also ich habe genug geschlafen, acht Stunden.
TH: I slept a little light, I had a little bit of deep sleep.
TH: Ich habe etwas leicht geschlafen, etwas wenig Tiefschlaf gehabt.
HK: What do you mean, easy sleep?
HK: Was meint das, wenn du sagst leicht geschlafen?
TH: Deep sleep is usually in the first, first half of sleep, and there, so the sleep phases are always alternating in these cycles, and the focus in the first half of sleep is on deep sleep, and that's for some reason,
TH: Der Tiefschlaf ist meistens in der ersten, ersten Hälfte des Schlafs und da, also die Schlafphasen wechseln sich ja immer ab in diesen Zyklen und der Schwerpunkt in der ersten Hälfte des Schlaf liegt auf dem Tiefschlaf und der ist aus irgendeinem Grund,
TH: I don't know, something came up short last night, tells me the recording of my watch.
TH: den ich nicht weiß, etwas zu kurz gekommen in der letzten Nacht, sagt mir die Aufzeichnung meiner Uhr.
HK: What do you pay attention to when you go to sleep?
HK: Worauf achtest du denn besonders, wenn du schlafen gehst?
TH: Regularity, so I'm really trying to go to bed at the same time and slowly slip into this sleep mode, doing similar things at the same time.
TH: Auf die Regelmäßigkeit, also ich versuche wirklich zur immer gleichen Zeit ins Bett zu gehen und langsam in diesen Schlafmodus hinein zu gleiten, ähnliche Dinge zu tun zur ähnlichen Zeit.
HK: And does it mean you always wake up at the same time?
HK: Und heißt es auch zur selben Zeit immer aufzuwachen?
TH: So that's the best way to do it, which is, of course, not always, depending on how the day goes, what's coming, but that's part of it.
TH: Das ergibt sich dann da möglichst daraus, das ist natürlich, geht nicht immer, je nachdem, wie der Tag so, was so ansteht, aber das gehört auch dazu.
HK: Can you actually go to bed or go to bed, so get some sleep?
HK: Kann man eigentlich vorschlafen oder nachschlafen, also Schlaf aufholen?
TH: Unfortunately, you can't sleep in advance.
TH: Leider nicht, leider kann man nicht vorschlafen.
TH: You can't sleep on supplies, which I think is great and practical, but unfortunately it's not possible.
TH: Man kann nicht auf Vorrat schlafen, das fände ich ganz toll und praktisch, aber es geht leider nicht.
TH: The regeneration processes have to come after what we've been burdened with, so you can't sleep in advance, unfortunately, unfortunately.
TH: Die Regenerationsprozesse müssen nach dem kommen, was uns belastet hat, deshalb kann man nicht vorschlafen, leider, leider.
HK: But can you go back to sleep?
HK: Aber man kann nachschlafen?
TH: You can get that back to a certain degree, but then of course you've spent some time in sleep deprivation, which is not that healthy, but obviously, so if you have a sleep deprivation, you can catch up, yeah.
TH: Man kann das wieder reinholen bis zum gewissen Grad, hat dann aber natürlich eine Zeit im Schlafdefizit verbracht, die nicht so gesund ist, aber klar, also wenn man ein Schlafdefizit hat, kann man das dann aufholen, ja.
HK: Well, in couples, the thing is, we'd rather sleep apart, so each for himself or for two, do you agree?
HK: Bei Paaren ist ja oft das Thema, schlafen wir lieber getrennt, also jeder für sich oder zu zweit, hast du da eine Meinung zu?
TH: So sleep is very individual, so I think I have an opinion for myself, I like to sleep in pairs, although it has disadvantages, but some people are more sensitive to it, and it can also make sense to sleep separately, so as with many questions about sleep, the answer is usually individual.
TH: Also Schlaf ist sehr individuell, ich glaube, ich habe eine Meinung für mich dazu, ich schlafe gerne zu zweit, obwohl es auch Nachteile hat, aber manche Leute sind da empfindlicher und es kann auch sinnvoll sein, getrennt zu schlafen, also wie bei vielen Fragen um den Schlaf ist die Antwort meistens individuell.
HK: And you have kids, too, I don't know how old they are, how are you doing with younger kids, how do you do it right as a parent, so that they learn healthy, good sleep?
HK: Und du hast auch Kinder, ich weiß jetzt nicht, wie alt die sind, wie ist das bei kleineren Kindern, wie macht man das als Eltern richtig, dass die einen gesunden und guten Schlaf lernen?
TH: So our youngest child is ten and then he's out of the deepest sleep, but it's known, anecdotally, I know that, and it's also been proven by studies that parents of young children typically have extreme sleep deficits, which is unfortunately the case.
TH: Also unser jüngstes Kind ist zehn und dann auch schon schlafmäßig aus dem gröbsten raus, aber es ist bekannt, anekdotisch weiß ich das und es ist auch durch Studien belegt, dass Eltern junger Kinder typischerweise ein extremes Schlafdefizit haben, das ist leider so.
TH: So there's a new study that says it can take six years for parents to get back to their healthy sleep pattern.
TH: Also es gibt eine neue Studie, die sagt, dass das sechs Jahre lang dauern kann, bis Eltern wieder in ihren gesunden Schlafrhythmus zurückfinden.
TH: So for the first time, it's normal and important to stay calm about all this, because if you're stressed out, it's easily passed on to the child.
TH: Also das erstmal ist das normal und wichtig ist, bei alledem gelassen zu bleiben, weil wenn man sich da noch zusätzlich stresst, das überträgt sich leicht aufs Kind.
TH: Because you say couples, it's really important to switch, which takes a lot of pressure off.
TH: Weil du sagst Paare, ist es wirklich wichtig sich abzuwechseln, das nimmt unheimlich viel Druck raus.
TH: It's also known that still mothers sleep significantly less than fathers.
TH: Es ist nämlich auch bekannt, dass immer noch die Mütter deutlich weniger schlafen als die Väter.
TH: I can confirm that.
TH: Das kann ich bestätigen.
TH: And it's really a huge relief to be switching.
TH: Und es ist echt eine riesen Entlastung, wenn man sich da abwechselt.
HK: But my question was more about the kids.
HK: Meine Frage eben zielte aber auch noch mehr auf die Kinder ab.
HK: So how do you teach kids to sleep well, to get through their sleep as soon as possible?
HK: Also wie bringt man Kindern bei, dass sie gut einschlafen können, dass sie möglichst bald durchschlafen können?
HK: I always liked to read to my child before bed at night.
HK: Ich habe meinem Kind immer gerne abends vorm Schlafengehen vorgelesen.
HK: I think that's recognized as good, right?
HK: Ich glaube, das ist anerkannt, dass das gut ist, oder?
TH: Yes, that's right.
TH: Ja, genau.
TH: Rituals.
TH: Rituale.
TH: Rituals are great.
TH: Rituale sind super.
TH: So sleep has a lot to do with regularity.
TH: Also Schlaf hat ganz viel mit Regelmäßigkeit zu tun.
TH: So unfortunately, we can't sleep on command, so we can eat on command or we can strain our muscles.
TH: Also wir können leider nicht auf Kommando einschlafen, also so wie wir auf Kommando essen können oder unsere Muskeln anspannen können.
TH: But we can use our habits program in the brain to find sleep.
TH: Aber wir können unser Gewohnheitsprogramm im Gehirn nutzen, um in den Schlaf zu finden.
HK: Do you know of any phases in your life where you suddenly find it harder to fall asleep or even get a good night's sleep?
HK: Kennst du aus deinem eigenen Leben Phasen, in denen plötzlich bei dir das Einschlafen oder auch das Durchschlafen wieder schwieriger geworden ist?
TH: Yes, yes.
TH: Ja, ja.
TH: So if you're upset inside, if you're busy with something.
TH: Also wenn man innerlich aufgewühlt ist, wenn einen irgendwas beschäftigt.
TH: That's often the first indication that something's wrong.
TH: Das ist oft auch so ein erster Hinweis, dass da irgendwas im Argen ist.
TH: I'm most likely to notice this in my sleep.
TH: Das merke ich am ehesten an meinem Schlaf.
HK: So what are you doing?
HK: Und was machst du dann?
TH: Well, I'm thinking about what this might be about.
TH: Naja, ich überlege erstmal, woran könnte das liegen?
TH: What's driving me?
TH: Was treibt mich denn eigentlich um?
HK: And how important are external factors?
HK: Und wie wichtig sind äußere Faktoren?
HK: So fresh air, open windows, not too hot, turn down heating, dark enough.
HK: Also frische Luft, geöffnetes Fenster, nicht zu warm, Heizung runterdrehen, dunkel genug.
HK: Is that really that important?
HK: Ist das wirklich so wichtig?
TH: Yes, that's important.
TH: Ja, das ist wichtig.
TH: Being able to sleep well is just about hormones.
TH: Gut einschlafen zu können hat halt schlicht mit Hormonen zu tun.
TH: And if you give your body the signal that it's actually a bright day, through bright or very energetic light, then you can't expect it to fall asleep easily.
TH: Und wenn man seinem Körper über helles oder sehr energiereiches Licht das Signal gibt, dass jetzt eigentlich heller Tag ist, dann kann man jetzt nicht erwarten, dass der leicht in den Schlaf findet.
TH: So that means that in time, the lighting dims a little bit, you put the buzzing devices away a little bit, and you lower the temperature in the bedroom.
TH: Das heißt also rechtzeitig die Beleuchtung ein bisschen dimmen, die bimmelnden Geräte ein bisschen weglegen und die Temperatur im Schlafzimmer absenken.
TH: So the optimal temperature for sleeping is all naturally studied, is amazingly low.
TH: Also die optimale Temperatur zum Schlafen ist alles natürlich untersucht, ist erstaunlich niedrig.
HK: How much is it?
HK: Bei wie viel liegt die?
TH: So it can be 15 degrees.
TH: Also die kann ruhig 15 Grad sein.
TH: I actually think the best interval is somewhere between 13 and 17 degrees.
TH: Ich glaube sogar, das beste Intervall ist irgendwie zwischen 13 und 17 Grad.
TH: So that's significantly below the temperature we normally have in our homes.
TH: Das ist also deutlich unter der Temperatur, die wir normalerweise in unseren Wohnungen haben.
HK: So I also opened the window halfway and turned the heater down, but I have a little tick.
HK: Also ich habe das Fenster auch halb geöffnet und die Heizung runtergedreht, aber ich habe einen kleinen Tick.
HK: I sleep under three blankets.
HK: Ich schlafe unter drei Decken.
HK: Is that bad?
HK: Ist das schlecht?
TH: It's also known that a thick blanket that exerts a little bit of pressure, so to speak, but it creates a sense of security that helps you sleep.
TH: Es ist auch bekannt, dass eine dicke Decke, die sozusagen so ein bisschen Druck ausübt, sondern Geborgenheitsgefühl erzeugt, das dem Schlafen hilft.
TH: That's been studied.
TH: Das ist auch untersucht.
HK: Tobias, you're also a great runner and I think you're a mountain climber.
HK: Tobias, du bist ja auch ein großer Läufer und ich glaube auch Bergsteiger.
HK: And do you actually spend nights outside in tents or even outdoors?
HK: Und verbringst du eigentlich auch Nächte draußen im Zelt oder sogar direkt unter freiem Himmel?
TH: Not in the open air anymore, but I like to spend nights outdoors.
TH: Unter freiem Himmel schon länger nicht, aber ich verbringe gerne Nächte draußen.
HK: What's so beautiful about that?
HK: Was ist da besonders schön?
TH: You don't necessarily sleep best, but it's just wonderful to be awakened by sunrise or by birds, and it's wonderful.
TH: Man schläft nicht unbedingt immer am besten, aber es ist einfach wunderbar, von dem Sonnenaufgang geweckt zu werden oder von den Vögeln und es ist herrlich.
TH: So I like to sleep in the mountains.
TH: Also ich schlafe gerne in den Bergen.
HK: Tobias, thank you for your tips.
HK: Tobias, vielen Dank für deine Tipps.
HK: The seven best sleep aids you've described in the current edition of Time Knowledge.
HK: Die sieben besten Einschlafhilfen, die beschreibst du in der aktuellen Ausgabe von Zeitwissen.
HK: And that's where our new series starts overnight.
HK: In der startet auch unsere neue Serie über die Nacht.
HK: We explain why people think, feel, and function differently at night.
HK: Wir erklären darin, warum der Mensch nachts anders denkt, anders fühlt und anders funktioniert.
HK: Which we can't explain.
HK: Was wir nicht erklären können.
HK: The impossible column by Christoph Drösser.
HK: Die unmögliche Kolumne von Christoph Drösser.
Christoph Drösser: Today, why do some people walk in their sleep?
Christoph Drösser: Heute, warum wandeln manche Menschen im Schlaf?
CD: The sleepwalker walking through the apartment with his arms outstretched and his eyes closed is a popular comic book cliché.
CD: Der Schlafwandler, der mit ausgestreckten Armen und geschlossenen Augen durch die Wohnung läuft, ist ein beliebtes Klischee im Comic.
CD: In reality, sleepwalkers behave almost normally, at least their gaze is a little stiff and their movements are uncertain.
CD: In der Realität verhalten sich Schlafwandler fast normal, allenfalls ihr Blick ist ein bisschen starr und ihre Bewegungen sind unsicher.
CD: And when they wake up, they don't remember anything.
CD: Und wenn sie aufwachen, erinnern sie sich an nichts.
HK: The problem is.
HK: Das Problem.
CD: On the one hand, sleepwalkers are sleeping, their consciousness is turned off.
CD: Einerseits schlafen Schlafwandler, ihr Bewusstsein ist ausgeschaltet.
CD: On the other hand, they're behaving like a vigilante.
CD: Andererseits verhalten sie sich wie ein wacher Mensch.
CD: How did this strange state of intermittent disorder, also called parasomnia, come about?
CD: Wie kommt es zu diesem seltsamen Zwischenzustand, der auch Parasomnie genannt wird?
SL: Which we already know.
SL: Was wir schon wissen.
CD: You can't cause sleepwalking to happen on purpose, because it's similar to physical phenomena like swallowing.
CD: Man kann das Schlafwandeln nicht gezielt hervorrufen, da ähnelt es körperlichen Phänomenen wie dem Schluck auf.
CD: So you can hardly test it in a sleep lab, for example.
CD: Man kann es also zum Beispiel kaum im Schlaflabor untersuchen.
CD: And because the sleepwalkers don't remember their nightly episodes later, there are no exact numbers.
CD: Und weil sich die Schlafwandler später nicht an ihre nächtlichen Episoden erinnern, gibt es keine exakten Zahlen.
CD: A review study estimates that 5% of all children and 1.5% of all adults have experienced a sleep change episode in the last 12 months.
CD: Eine Überblickstudie schätzt, dass 5% aller Kinder und 1,5% aller Erwachsenen in den letzten zwölf Monaten eine Schlafwandel-Episode erlebt haben.
CD: Sleepwalking occurs in the deep sleep phase, not in the REM sleep we dream of.
CD: Das Schlafwandeln tritt in der Tiefschlafphase auf, nicht im REM-Schlaf, in dem wir träumen.
CD: The episodes can last up to half an hour, and the affected persons may perform some of the most complex tasks.
CD: Die Episoden können bis zu einer halben Stunde andauern, die Betroffenen können teilweise komplexe Tätigkeiten ausführen.
CD: A lot of people are making something to eat.
CD: Viele machen sich etwas zu essen.
CD: And an American sleepwalker drove 23 kilometers to his mother-in-law, who he then killed.
CD: Und ein amerikanischer Schlafwandler ist 23 Kilometer mit dem Auto gefahren zu seiner Schwiegermutter, die er dann umgebracht hat.
CD: But most sleep transformers don't pose a risk to outsiders.
CD: Aber die meisten Schlafwandler stellen kein Risiko für Außenstehende dar.
CD: And the full moon has nothing to do with sleepwalking.
CD: Und mit dem Vollmond hat das Schlafwandeln überhaupt nichts zu tun.
CD: There are a few factors that favor sleep change.
CD: Es gibt einige Faktoren, die das Schlafwandeln begünstigen.
CD: The common sleep patterns of children as adults may have something to do with their brain not being fully developed.
CD: Das kinderhäufige Schlafwandeln als Erwachsene kann damit zu tun haben, dass ihr Gehirn noch nicht vollständig entwickelt ist.
CD: There is a distinct genetic factor.
CD: Es gibt einen eindeutigen genetischen Faktor.
CD: Children with two parents who are sleepwalking are three times more likely to be affected than others.
CD: Kinder mit zwei schlafwandelnden Eltern sind dreimal so häufig betroffen wie andere.
CD: Mental illness promotes sleep patterns, and it occurs four to six times more often in people with migraines and Tourette syndrome than in the general population.
CD: Psychische Krankheiten begünstigen das Schlafwandeln und bei Migränekranken und vom Tourette-Syndrom Betroffenen tritt es vier- bis sechsmal so häufig auf wie in der Gesamtbevölkerung.
CD: Sleep deprivation and chronic fatigue seem to favor the phenomenon.
CD: Schlafmangel und chronische Übermüdung scheinen das Phänomen zu begünstigen.
CD: Especially children often go to sleep when they have a fever.
CD: Besonders Kinder schlafwandeln häufig dann, wenn sie Fieber haben.
CD: And in women, the frequency fluctuates with the menstrual cycle.
CD: Und bei Frauen schwankt die Häufigkeit mit dem Menstruationszyklus.
CD: But these are all statistical statements.
CD: Das alles sind aber statistische Aussagen.
CD: How all these conditions actually affect the brain and disrupt the wake mechanism, science can't tell.
CD: Wie all diese Bedingungen tatsächlich im Gehirn wirken und den Aufwachmechanismus stören, kann die Wissenschaft nicht sagen.
CD: There are no clinical studies on sleepwalking.
CD: Klinische Studien zum Schlafwandeln gibt es nicht.
CD: Sleepwalking is not really a disease, either.
CD: Schlafwandeln ist aber auch nicht wirklich eine Krankheit.
CD: The only negative consequences are accidents that happen during night trips.
CD: Die einzigen negativen Folgen sind Unfälle, die während der nächtlichen Ausflüge passieren.
CD: Well, that's probably why there's not a lot of research on this phenomenon, and it's also because the causes of sleep change are unclear.
CD: Wohl auch deshalb wird nicht sehr intensiv über das Phänomen geforscht und auch damit hat es zu tun, dass die Ursachen des Schlafwandels ungeklärt sind.
CD: One more thing, if you live with a sleepwalker, don't wake him or her up brutally.
CD: Eine Sache noch, wenn Sie mit einem Schlafwandler zusammenleben, wecken Sie ihn oder sie nicht brutal auf.
CD: It confuses the people involved.
CD: Das verwirrt die Betroffenen.
CD: Take the person carefully by the shoulder and lead them back to bed.
CD: Fassen Sie die Person behutsam an der Schulter und führen Sie sie zurück zum Bett.
CD: Then you usually fall asleep.
CD: Dann schläft der Mensch meist problemlos wieder ein.
HK: In the current Time Science issue, I'd like to recommend two more pieces for the night.
HK: In der aktuellen Zeitwissenausgabe möchte ich Ihnen gern noch zwei weitere Stücke zur Nacht empfehlen.
HK: Nils Böhing reports on his trip through Europe in three-night trains.
HK: Nils Böhing berichtet von seiner Expedition durch Europa in Dreinachtzügen.
HK: And what's definitely helping with poor sleep is winter bathing.
HK: Und was mit Sicherheit bei schlechtem Einschlafen hilft, ist Winterbaden.
HK: If you dive in two degrees of cold water, you're guaranteed to be tired at night.
HK: Wer in zwei Grad kaltes Wasser taucht, ist abends garantiert müde.
HK: You can get a free trial of the Time Know Magazine at time.de slash know minus podcast.
HK: Eine kostenlose Probeausgabe des Zeitwissen Magazins erhalten Sie unter zeit.de slash wissen minus podcast.
HK: And we're excited about feedback and ideas.
HK: Und über Feedback und Ideen freuen wir uns.
HK: Please write to us at podcast at time minus know point.de.
HK: Schreiben Sie uns bitte an podcast at zeit minus wissen punkt.de.
HK: My name is Hella Kemper and I'll see you soon.
HK: Ich bin Hella Kemper und wir hören uns bald wieder.